After studying nearly 3,000 paywalls,
hundreds of subscription flows on Moby,
and talking to someone who's designed
over 4,700 paywalls,
we found this.
>> [music]
>> Sometimes, an ugly paywall could
outperform a beautiful one.
>> No matter what I did, the ugly paywall
with a ton of text completely over
performed anything that I would do.
>> More friction could increase
conversions.
>> Multi-page paywalls almost always do
better than single-page paywalls.
>> Every paywall today kind of looks the
same. So, I wanted to know what
separates a high-performing paywall from
an average one.
I used to think the decision happens on
a paywall, but actually, users sometimes
decide to pay before they even see the
paywall.
>> All the different touchpoints are
extremely important.
>> The paywall can appear after onboarding,
when you unlock a premium feature,
inside settings, [music]
or even as a win-back offer before you
leave.
>> Those paywalls speak more to the user
because they're more personalized.
You're constantly trying to get the user
to either pay or stay as a subscribing
member, and so you have to think about
the entire life cycle of the customer.
And yes, product is important for being
able to solve a problem, but life cycle
monetization and the paywalls, that's
the only part of the app that makes
money.
>> A paywall isn't just a screen. It's a
flow.
Before asking for money, Opal spends
time selling the outcome, getting 8
years of your life back. By the time you
reach the paywall, it doesn't feel like
[music] an interruption.
By showing users how many years of their
life they could save, trial sign-ups
went up from 7% to 17%.
Jonathan prefers multi-page paywalls.
>> Multi-page paywalls almost always do
better than single-page paywalls. And
so, in this paywall, you're at the end
of the customer journey and onboarding,
and you've just showed the customer that
hey, your plan is ready. This is what
you can expect. You're speaking to them
from an emotional perspective. You're
telling them they're going to start
feeling like themselves in 4 weeks or
you're going to tell them something that
is in line with their actual ideal
outcome. Does the paywall already feel
part of the experience? Like if it's an
onboarding, is it a natural segue to
kind of finish the onboarding?
>> A Head takes a similar approach.
Information unfolds gradually. It gives
users time to process the decision
instead of forcing them to absorb
everything at once.
I think when a paywall works, it doesn't
feel like you've hit a wall. It feels
like the product is asking you to take
the natural next step.
Even if you have a well-designed
paywall, [music] if it appears at the
wrong moment, it's still a bad paywall.
One example is the one-time offer. If
you close it, it's gone. Paired with
animation and haptic feedback, this
helps to pull the attention of the user
the moment that you're considering an
upgrade. Even when the timing is right,
people can still hesitate. Will I forget
to cancel? Am I making the right
decision? And that's why some of the
best-performing paywalls focus on
reducing risk. Blinkist had a problem.
Their users complained about free trials
because they felt tricked into being
charged. So, they redesigned the paywall
screen to show a step-by-step timeline.
The result was more trial sign-ups,
fewer complaints. Push notification
opt-ins also went up, which makes sense
because they remind you before your
trial ends.
>> [music]
>> Tipstop emphasized the free trial, added
a discount badge, and made the offer
easier to understand. The offer didn't
change. The way it was presented [music]
did. Direct conversions almost tripled.
And then there's Slopes. Instead of
redesigning the paywall, they asked a
different question. What if we got rid
of the paywall altogether? They took
inspiration from Apple's redeem free
trial approach and built what they call
a pay ramp. Users see a single action,
redeem your free week. No traditional
paywall standing in the way. This alone
increased trial starts by 25%.
Which brings us to one of Jonathan's
favorite paywall tweaks.
>> This no commitment cancel anytime
subtitle always seems to do well. Adding
it to the paywall will bump things up
incrementally. And then also having some
kind of call to action for what the user
is doing instead of just continue is hit
or miss, but I do like to experiment
with that as well. Another thing too is
like having this right chevron here on
the button. I can't make a judgement yet
as to whether like this in itself does
the best because I have not done a test
yet where everything is the same except
for this right chevron, but in most of
the paywalls that end up winning, they
have this right chevron. So, I've also
started to include it on the button
along with this subtitle here.
>> Jonathan takes this idea one step
further.
>> So, if they try to hit cancel over here,
I like to show the users an exit intent
sheet. If they're not ready to commit
for a year, you can still subscribe to
the monthly plan.
>> And when we talked about aggressive last
minute discounts?
>> I wouldn't really do this unless it's
maybe Cyber Monday Black Friday. I'm
really curious to see how Apple is going
to approach that this year for all these
different sales, but to make sure that
I'm compliant and safe, I'd recommend
instead to have an offer with a larger
trial.
>> Giving users a longer trial could help
you achieve the same goal while
preserving trust. So, if reducing risk
helps with conversions, we would expect
that removing friction will do the same.
But that's not the case.
To start your free trial on Outsider,
>> [music]
>> you'll need to enter your credit card
details. Sign-ups dropped by more than
half, but the conversion rates increased
by five times, more than double the
paying customers.
The extra friction filtered out people
who were never serious in the first
place. Moonly discovered something
similar. They introduced a free trial,
but only on the annual plan.
Sometimes what changes isn't the offer,
it's how the offer is framed. One of the
most common techniques is social proof
with real user reviews and a five-star
rating.
>> These social accolades are really nice
to kind of show credibility and
authority.
>> The second common technique is value
framing.
>> [music]
>> You're framing the value in such a way
that it matches what the users care
about. All these screens are selling
different futures. [music]
And then there's price anchoring.
Tide breaks down the price into smaller
weekly amounts. Ahead compares its
subscription to things people already
spend money on, like coffee or therapy.
Next up, pricing and packaging.
Headspace [music] tested 7-day, 14-day,
and 30-day free trials. The winning
variant was this, 14-day trial for
[music] the annual plan. Even though the
annual plan costs more, the longer trial
made the whole decision feel less risky.
If you're wondering what the best
pricing structure is, [music] it depends
on what you're optimizing for.
>> Ideally, you want to default to a yearly
product because we see that that has the
highest LTV, but a yearly product may
not be the best for your business. If
you need to, you have that yearly
product with [music] a weekly or with a
monthly product. You only want to show
two to decrease cognitive load on the
user. So, if you do want to support
other pricing options, you always hide
it behind a view all plans button that
opens up a sheet with all the different
pricing. You want to keep the base
paywall simple, get a bunch of users in
there to see how your base stats perform
before you go crazy on optimizing all
your different placements.
>> Jonathan is also a big believer in
table-based [music]
paywalls.
>> I am a huge fan of tables. They're a
little hard to build in Superwall. I
think that's maybe why, like in
RevenueCat and Superwall, I'm not really
seeing a lot of tables. These also do a
good job of showcasing what you're
missing out on if you don't subscribe.
This also works pretty well. A video
paywall showing you the app in action
and simple bullet list, simple social
proof here of people already using your
app.
>> Video could communicate value faster
than static screenshots or bullet
points. Now, one thing we kept coming
back to was polish.
>> I think animations work really well.
There's an app that I really like right
now that's going viral. It's called
Focus Town, and they've done an amazing
job of branding and creating a Animal
Crossing-esque experience, and that's
the level of polish that we're going to
be seeing from the most successful apps
moving forward. You know, the bar has
just been raised because now that anyone
can ship an app, the ones that really
put in the time to polish it with
animations, with custom character
designs, with world building are going
to be the most successful moving
forward.
>> When two products are competing for the
same user, polish could be the reason
why someone chooses your product over
the others. [music] If you're building
with AI, that's exactly what Mobbin MCP
is for. It gives tools like Claude,
ChatGPT, and Cursor access to Mobbin's
library. So, instead of making things
up, [music] your AI can reference
patterns that already exist in the real
world, compare how apps design their
paywalls, and pull examples directly
into your workflow. Think of it as
grounding your AI's output in what's
already been shipped.
Not every pattern is worth copying.
Some of the highest converting paywalls
are the ones Jonathan is the most
skeptical of. The same tactics you'll
find in drop shipping stores and
e-commerce websites.
>> So, one paywall that works extremely
well that I really have a hard time
accepting is the spin the wheel paywall.
This is a predetermined spin the wheel
Lottie file that may land on some kind
of discounted percentage. You know, the
user gets to claim it and then cuz
they've just won something, the idea is
that they'll uh be more likely to then
subscribe at that price point. If you're
optimizing for a longer-term business,
that may not be a good paywall for you.
But, if you're optimizing for a weekly
price and you want to maximize revenue,
unfortunately, it works. The issue is
that everyone is also starting to use it
or I'm seeing it used a lot more.
>> When every app uses fake urgency
tactics, users eventually stop believing
it.
>> I think more and more users are getting
comfortable closing paywalls because
they know they're going to get some kind
of offer afterwards.
>> And in early 2026, Apple also started
rejecting paywall patterns that relied
on free trial toggles because some of
these were considered confusing or
misleading.
>> Just remember that this is a long-term
game.
>> Jonathan once worked with an AI
girlfriend app.
>> They had probably the ugliest paywall
I've ever seen and it was really compact
elements, very aggressive squeeze page
kind of paywall. So, that ended up
over-performing pretty much any paywall
that I tried to do.
>> Which means that there is literally no
universal best paywall, only better
experiments.
>> One thing that I learned from Jake and
Nick at Superwall was that design tests
move the needle the most. We ended up
running radically [music] different
designs until you find something that
blows everything out of the water. You
could have a video paywall, you could
have bullet list paywall, a trial
timeline paywall, a long-form [music]
paywall.
>> Test every copy, the pricing, the flow
until something clearly wins. Getting
people to subscribe is one thing.
Building something that people continues
to pay for [music] is much harder.
>> The metrics that I wish more founders
really care the most about is retention
and LTV. I think if retention and LTV
are good, you're building a good product
and you want to build good products so
that the ecosystem is flourishing in
itself. So,
>> maybe the question isn't how do I get
people to [music] pay? It's more of how
could I create something worth paying
for?
Fun fact,
>> [music]
>> it takes less than five screens to
subscribe to ClassPass, but 17 screens
to cancel. Let us know if you'd like us
to dive into cancellation flows or
anything else in the comments below.
Next, watch our breakdown on onboarding
flows, dashboard designs,
and the psychology behind streaks.
I'll see you there.