At some point, keeping my streak alive
mattered more than actually learning.
Why does breaking a streak feel so
terrible? And are streaks actually
helping us build habits or just making
us afraid to stop?
Here's what I found after looking at 859
streak designs on Mobbin. Every streak
design revolves around this question.
What makes us come back tomorrow? Let's
start with the most obvious pattern,
fear. Let's say you won $10 today. It
feels nice. Now, imagine losing $10
instead. It stings way more.
This is what we call loss aversion.
Streak mechanics bet on this.
The copy becomes more urgent.
The clock starts counting down.
And look, an angry owl giving you a
sense of guilt. Fear-based streaks work
because we're protecting something we
could lose.
Now, some streak systems lean on
optimism. These designs make us feel
like we're building towards a better
version of ourselves.
Copy is positive and encouraging.
Even tiny shifts to calls to actions.
Duolingo's product team tested these
copy changes. We used to say continue
and we changed that to commit to my goal
and it was like a massive win.
More and more apps are doing this today.
Reframing a call to action into a
promise you make to yourself.
Some apps even turn streaks into
collectibles, like badges, milestones,
and tangible proof of progress.
In Opal, your streak earns you literal
milestones that you can collect over
time.
I noticed I wasn't opening Duolingo
because I cared about the streak number
anymore. I opened because I didn't want
to disappoint Duo. It's just a cartoon
owl, just pixels, but I still felt it.
So, I looked into why.
When we assign human emotions to
non-human things, it's called
anthropomorphism.
That's why we yell at computers, name
our cars, and apologize [music] to AI.
Software uses this, too.
A mascot cheering you on like it
believes in you.
A little bird growing alongside you.
So, back in the '90s, people got
emotionally attached to these tiny
virtual pets you had to feed [music] and
care for. Tamagotchi, the original
virtual reality pet. Your care
determines the pets you get from Bandai.
If you ignored your Tamagotchi, they
would literally die.
People carried them everywhere, even
grieved when they died. This is called
the Tamagotchi effect. It's the
attachment that forms when a digital
thing appears to need you back.
Duolingo took it further than most.
It became a personality. I realized that
mascots aren't just there to make apps
feel cute. They're designed to create
attachment.
The moment you feel something for a
product, the barrier to leaving feels a
lot higher. And maybe that's why we care
so much about a cartoon owl.
Some streak systems don't rely on fear,
hope, or attachment. They work through
visual attention.
They all turn consistency into a visible
pattern. Once there's a gap, our brain
notices it immediately.
Part of this relates to the Zeigarnik
effect. Unfinished things stay active in
our mind longer than completed ones.
That's why filling one tiny missing
block feels strangely satisfying, and
why breaking the chain feels worse than
it probably should.
These mechanics are everywhere, even in
places that have nothing to do with
self-improvement. Different interfaces
with the same underlying idea, giving
[music] people something they don't want
to break. These patterns keep pulling us
back, but why? What's actually working
here?
We tend to think dopamine is the
chemical our brain releases after
something rewarding happens, but
Professor Schultz found that dopamine
doesn't just respond to rewards. It
responds to the prediction of rewards.
[music]
The smell of coffee before our first
sip, the notification chime before we
even read it. Our brain starts to
reacting to [music] what it thinks is
coming next, which means a streak
doesn't need to feel satisfying every
single time. It just needs to make our
brain feel like something satisfying is
about to happen. And that's exactly what
the habit loop is built around. Almost
every habit follows the same four
stages. The first stage, cue, something
that triggers the anticipation before we
even open the app. Then comes craving.
The Duolingo jingle after each lesson
makes us want the next one.
Next, response. Make it easy so we'll do
it, like auto progressing to the next
step. Finally, the reward. [music]
It's that satisfying feeling our brain
spent the last minute anticipating.
Studies found that when people are
reminded of their streak, just seeing
the number, they're more likely to keep
going. We haven't even opened the app
yet, but the cue already triggered the
loop. That's what makes us want to come
back tomorrow, not the lesson, not even
the streak, but the habit loop itself.
But if just seeing the streak is enough
to pull us back in, why do people give
up entirely after breaking a streak? The
longer the streak, the more our identity
gets wrapped up in it.
The obvious solution to this would be
making your streaks stricter, adding
more pressure and accountability, but
Duolingo found the opposite worked
better. They implemented a feature
called streak freeze that lets you miss
a day without losing everything. And
when Duolingo allowed users to equip up
to two streak freezes at a time, daily
active learners increased by 0.38%.
That's over 200,000 more people coming
back every day. People were more likely
to keep going after failure when goals
included a little built-in flexibility.
Duolingo tested two variants. First,
users must hit their full daily goal in
order to preserve the streak.
The second variant is where users could
keep their streak alive by just
completing one lesson on Duolingo.
This variant won.
Over 40% more people maintained their
7-day streak. More and more apps are
designing streaks around recovery
instead of perfection. Repairs, freezing
your streaks, pauses, and giving people
grace days. But that raises a bigger
question. Do streaks actually help
people build long-term habits or are
they just really good at making people
come back? [music]
On hindsight, streaks seem like the
perfect habit-building system. All we
need to do is to show up every day and
eventually the behavior became
automatic. But the more I research, the
more I notice that most evidence around
streaks focuses on engagement and
retention, not necessarily lasting
behavioral change.
We know that dopamine responds to the
prediction or the anticipation of
reward. But once the streak becomes
routine, when things become predictable,
that dopamine signal actually weakens.
So, apps keep layering in new surprises.
Animations,
milestone celebrations,
bonus XP.
They're all manufacturing
unpredictability to keep the loop alive.
But, optimizing for engagement and
optimizing for long-term habit formation
is not the same thing. So, what actually
makes habits stick?
Most streak systems are designed around
never missing a day, right? We got to
show up every single day to keep our
streak moving.
A study tracked people building real
habits over months and found that
missing a day had almost no effect on
whether the behavior eventually became
automatic. People simply resumed and the
[music] habit continued, which is the
opposite of how most streak systems are
designed.
Maybe what matters isn't how long you
keep your streak. It's whether you come
back even after breaking it. And that's
[music] good news to me. Now I know that
one bad day doesn't erase everything.
Next, watch what we learned from
analyzing a thousand onboarding flows
and what separates intuitive dashboards
from overwhelming ones across 2,000
dashboard designs. Be sure to subscribe
for our next deep dive on paywalls.