There's a reason Dolingo, Revolute, and
Phantom all blew up, and it's the same
hidden edge I found designing for
startups and tech giants alike for the
last decade. It's called emotional
design. The art of making products feel
engaging, personal, and alive. And in
this video, I'll show you how to use it
to build apps people love and keep
coming back to. Let's be honest, these
days, anyone can build something fast.
We have APIs, no code tools, AI models.
All the ingredients are out there. It's
easier than ever to build things and
ship features, which means just being
useful isn't enough anymore. The real
edge is in how your product makes people
feel when they open it. Does it feel
smooth, delightful, playful, or even
premium? Or does it just feel like every
other app? Now, of course, winning
products still come from a mix of smart
things, like having a solid business
model, good timing, maybe even a strong
community. The list goes on. But more
and more, the thing that truly separates
good from great is design that connects,
design that feels intentional, design
that turns users into fans. There's this
quote from Reed Hastings, Netflix
co-founder, and it really nails the
point. The product has to be so good
people want to talk about it. And in a
world where every product has the same
access to tech, that's your long-term
edge. Not the code, not the features.
It's how your product leaves people
feeling when they close the tab or swipe
away. Now, before we dig into one of the
best examples of emotional design
translating into serious business
growth, if you're wondering how this
might apply to your product or your
business, we open up a couple of free
design strategy consultations each month
at SIPAP. So, feel free to sign up in
the link down below if that sounds
interesting. Now, with that, let's look
at Dualingo and how they used delight,
feedback, and character motion to pull
users in and keep them coming back.
Because Duolingo didn't just create
another language learning app, they
built a product that responds to you in
real time and in a way that actually
feels human. In 2022, they introduced a
full character animation system. This
included things like facial reactions,
lip syncing with audio, and idle
animations that made their characters
feel alive even when you weren't doing
anything. And this wasn't just for show.
Duolingo's data shows that after these
animations were rolled out, their daily
active users more than doubled from 14.2
million to over 34 million within 2
years. On top of that, their paid
subscribers also more than doubled in
that same time frame. Of course, again,
growth like that comes from a mix of
smart moves like adding new languages,
improving the curriculum, running solid
marketing campaigns, etc. But what's
interesting is that Dualingo's own team
has highlighted character animation as
one of the major reasons people stay
engaged. On several occasions, CEO Luis
Vonan has pointed out that the app's
delightful experience, which includes
these animations, sets it apart in a
space full of dry, functional apps. And
that connection isn't random. These
animations aren't just eye candy.
They're emotional feedback. They create
loops that keep people engaged. When you
answer a question correctly or make a
mistake, you don't just get a green
check mark. You feel encouraged,
corrected, and even cheered on. Those
quick reactions help boost engagement by
triggering emotional feedback loops,
something that the UX legend Don Norman
talks a lot about in his book, Emotional
Design. But how can you use this in your
own product? Well, if your product
relies on repeated user behavior, like
check-ins, journaling, or habit logging,
add micro interactions that give instant
emotional feedback. A subtle bounce, a
glow, a sparkle. These little things can
make confirmation moments feel a little
more rewarding. Also, celebrate the
small wins. This will reinforce
engagement. Once again, you know,
success states don't need to be huge,
but they should feel intentional. Also,
if you're like Dualingo and you have a
mascot of some sort, use the mascot to
show expressions, to encourage users
because emotions are contagious. This
can be small nods, smiles, or animated
reactions that make the experience feel
more human. And lastly, if you want to
give the user a feeling of momentum,
include nice progress animations. This
can be anything like using motion to
show streaks just like Dualingo or
showing different levels, showing
journals completed, whatever gives a
sense of building something over time.
The goal here is to make the feedback
feel human, not just functional, because
that kind of emotional layer can quietly
build a strong connection between the
user and your product. Even something
super simple, when done well, can make
the experience feel more alive and more
worth coming back to. So, Duolingo built
habits by using design to make people
feel good about using the app. And that
feeling is one of the main reasons their
users keep showing up. But what happens
when your users aren't trying to form
habits? When they instead are trying to
get over skepticism? That's one of the
big challenges that crypto apps face and
the problem that Phantom set out to
solve with the help of emotional design
and animation. Let's start by just
dropping the bomb. Crypto UX is
notoriously clunky. And Phantom knew
that. So when they rolled out a full
brand refresh in mid 2023, they didn't
just change their logo. They overhauled
everything and brought in animation to
shift perception. They animated their
ghost mascot. They added playful
animations during wallet creation. And
they put a bunch of effort into making
each interaction feel playful and
approachable. The goal was clear here.
Make crypto feel less scary and more
human. And it's obviously worked. Today,
Phantom is one of crypto's mostused
wallets, recently becoming the second
highest ranked app in the utilities
category in the US app store, beating
apps like WhatsApp and Instagram. Now,
just like Dualingo, Phantom's growth
rode the wave of market momentum and
smart business execution. But what
really made them stand out was how
design-led they were from the jump.
Their CEO, Brandon Milman, has been
super clear about that. This wasn't just
another wallet. From day one, the team
focused on polish, on craft, and on
building something that actually felt
good to use. In his own words, polish
matters. We're a design-led company that
takes time to craft polished products.
And that mindset paid off because while
most wallets were built by developers
for other developers, Phantom focused on
consumers. Their goal was to onboard the
next billion people to web 3. And that
meant investing in crisp, emotional UI
and animations. So when designing in
spaces that feel intimidating, complex,
or where the stakes are really high,
like finance, crypto, health, or
insurance, for example, remember these
principles. Polish builds trust. Treat
visual details, motion, and transitions
as core product features, not fluff.
Every little micro interaction is a
trust signal. Also, try to keep it
approachable. Friendly visuals and warm,
playful details make heavy topics feel a
little lighter, and that goes a long way
in building confidence. Build for
people, not just pros. Don't just assume
that users know the rules. Design flows
that make sense to everyday people,
especially if you're reaching beyond
early adopters. Performance matters, but
what really sticks is how the product
feels when someone taps, swipes, or
waits. Giving the users smooth feedback
is going to increase their confidence
with your product. As an agency that has
experience helping drive big design
results in the crypto industry, we try
to share some of our learnings by
writing case studies about our wins
every now and then. If you're interested
in that, there's a link below for that,
too. Now, we've seen how character and
delight create trust, but trust isn't
the end goal for everyone. So, let's
explore how emotional design and motion
can be used in an even more lucrative
way to sell luxury, which brings us to
Revolute. Revolute's been investing in
design and animation for years. But
what's super interesting is how their
design glow up has tracked right
alongside their push into more of the
premium space. As they've moved up
market, their visual language has gotten
way more polished and it's pretty clear
that they've been intentional about
this, aligning how the product feels
with where they want the business to go.
Take the first time user experience as
an example. They don't just drop you
into a boring signup flow. Instead, you
get rich visuals, super smooth
transitions, and right away, it feels
like you're stepping into something
premium. I mean, even their charts
leveled up. You don't just look at your
spending data, you feel it. You drag
your finger and the graph responds with
this soft glow, turning numbers into
something way more tactile. The same
thing with their cards. You don't just
see a static image. You get a full
little 3D moment there. The card flips,
rotates, catches light. It's clean. It's
intentional. And it's honestly just kind
of satisfying. And these little details
like subtle animations in security flows
or onboarding provide that sense of
trust without trying too hard. None of
these design details shout at you, but
together they create something way more
premium. And in fintech in particular,
where trust literally affects how much
users spend, that kind of polish
translates straight into revenue. So
here's the big takeaway. Nail the first
impression. Spend time to polish your
onboarding. Polish your welcome moments
to immediately communicate quality,
trust, and care. Add subtle moments of
delight like animations, like fades and
hover effects or gestures. Build that
emotion and make touch points feel
intentional. Make interactions feel
dynamic. So, tactile charts, responsive
feedback, or animated cards that just
turn basic features into something that
feels elevated and engaging. Now, if you
found this video helpful at all, you
will probably love the video here
somewhere. Also, if you're building a
product, a website, or a brand, and you
want to find out how to boost your top
business metrics through design, well,
consider our free strategy consultation.
The links still down below. Still down
below, still above law. Until the next
one, have a great