I've studied over a thousand onboarding
flows to find out what makes good
onboarding and do we even need one? A
lot of what I've read says keep it
short, but based on what I found, the
average app has 25 onboarding screens.
The longest categories are finance,
[music] health and fitness, and
education. Seven out of 10 of these
longest apps are actually finance apps
as [music] well. Some of the apps with
the longest onboarding flows are also
one of the most successful ones. When we
look at apps with the shortest
onboarding flows, three of them are AI
products. So, maybe keeping our
onboarding flows short was never the
point. The best onboarding seem to
follow this pattern.
>> [music]
>> You sign up, set up your account, you
hit the aha moment. That's where you
actually feel the product's value. For
Airbnb, it's making your first booking.
For Netflix, it's finding and watching a
show. For Mobbin, it's finding a screen
or an animation that you love and saving
it to your collection. So, what are
these apps actually doing? The best
onboarding screens I've kept seeing had
one thing in common. They're not listing
features, they're selling the outcome.
Timehop does this really simply.
>> [music]
>> Their welcome screen is just showing the
product in action on both their mobile
app and desktop.
Runkeeper does this with animation. The
moment you open the app, you get a feel
for what it does without reading a
single word. And Elma [music] goes one
step further. It lets you try the core
experience before you sign up. I rarely
see apps with AI features who lets you
try it out before signing up an account.
[music]
And sometimes it could just be a copy
tweak like Superhuman. They turn a
boring sign up screen into a pitch with
logos on the side as social proof. Some
apps skip the pitch entirely and just
feel human. This is an app called One
Year. So, in their onboarding flow, they
included a founder's note, which had
[music] a handwritten signature and a
hand-drawn flower in it.
It's pretty cute. And Tinder [music]
acknowledge when your birthday is around
the corner.
Airbnb, well, this one's not even in the
onboarding flow, but when you
successfully list your first space, they
show you a video from their CEO.
It's a founder's touch at the aha
moment.
As for Basecamp, they put a personal
note from the CEO after you've created
an account. It feels like the product
was made with intention. And one of the
best onboarding flows add
personalization into the flow, and they
make it worth your time. 23% of apps
personalize during onboarding, with AI
apps at only 7%. It seems like AI tools
don't ask questions about your users up
front. They let the product learn from
us instead.
Looking at Tide's onboarding, it's short
and sweet. You just download the app,
answer two questions, watch it customize
your recommendations,
and it'll prompt you to sign up. That's
it, very simple.
Headspace found out that their users
come to their app with more than one
pain point to solve. So, instead of
asking users to pick just one goal that
they want to achieve [music] with
Headspace, they let them pick more than
one. It's only like a very simple tweak,
but it led to 10% increase in free trial
conversion. There are also other apps
that allow multi-intent queries. [music]
Focus Flight lets you choose your map
style during onboarding. It makes the
app [music] feel like yours before you
even started using it. Sometimes,
[music] it can be even simpler than
that. Dollar Shave Club tweaked the quiz
copy to be more conversational. This
alone led to 5% increase in
subscriptions. Some apps don't just
collect answers during the quiz. They
actually show you what those answers
unlocked. So, in Endless onboarding, you
answer six questions,
and then they show you this. You haven't
even used the product yet, but it
already feels like it's going to work.
[music]
Byte Pal does the same thing. After the
quiz, they build your personal plan and
then tell you exactly when you'll hit
your goal.
Brilliant [music] shows you courses that
are personalized to your responses.
As soon as you finish your onboarding
flow, your home page is already
populated with only the content that you
want to see.
Here's another one by Speak, a language
learning app. They ask you what language
you'd like to learn and your goals.
Then, in one simple screen, it tells
you, "In 2 months, you'll be able to
communicate while traveling in France."
There's a simple graph showing that
speaking helps you reach your goals
faster than reading. The [music] steps
before this screen already had you
speaking instead of typing.
So, out of 900-plus
apps and websites, 22% [music] of them
throws a paywall during onboarding. Some
apps also pair personalization with a
paywall.
The site pairs a quiz with a one-time
offer to drive urgency.
Timely does the same with a full page of
social proof before showing the paywall.
And Focus Flight makes the paywall
itself fun. The one-time offer, it's
shaped like a flight ticket, and your
phone vibrates as it gets printed out.
It's a paywall that actually feels
delightful. As for Grammarly, based on
your quiz answers, they recommend
tailored pricing plans. This alone led
to almost a 20% increase in plan
upgrades. Okay, some of these onboarding
flows are really long, yet they don't
feel like it. The onboarding flows that
I really love tend to make onboarding
flows feel short.
Out of 986 apps, Duolingo has one one
the longest onboarding flows. And if we
zoom in, it goes like this. You get
started, choose the language that you
want to learn, it learns about you, you
start your first lesson, get the
satisfaction of completing it, and then
you create an account. By that point,
you've already gone through 60 screens
before you even sign up. And the crazy
part is it doesn't even feel long. Okay,
so Bump's onboarding flow is creative.
Even the loading states are wild.
There's always something going on
throughout the onboarding flow. Smooth
animations on things like verification
that rarely [music] get special
treatment. It adds fun. It doesn't feel
like you're going through a boring
onboarding flow.
Bipul has 61 screens. The onboarding was
a lot of fun. It has really amazing
animations. The raccoon is quite
lovable. And you even get to name your
virtual pet raccoon.
Throughout the onboarding, they
emphasize the value. Like, your personal
plan is ready and you'll lose weight by
an exact date. And then bam, a paywall.
All right. So, another pattern I
noticed, some apps don't front-load all
the education to you. Cake Equity is a
great example. They're dealing with dry
concepts like company equity and vesting
schedules, and turns it into something
approachable with copy that reassures
users from time to time, and tooltips
that explain the impact of each step so
[music] that users feel like someone's
guiding them along the way. Even
something as small as a password field
that checks off requirements in real
time as you type, removes a reason to
get stuck. Maybe it's a progress
indicator, maybe it's microcopy. None of
this is flashy, but it makes the
experience feel effortless. To-do apps
does this really well, too. Instead of
giving users a blank empty state, they
show you something like this with no
guided tours, no pop-ups, just a little
nudge in the right place.
And when Mural replaced pop-ups and
banners with a clear six-step checklist,
it drove a 10% relative increase in
one-week retention. Checklists stick
around even after the user dismisses the
initial flow.
If you go on Mobbin and do an AI search
for onboarding checklist, you will find
more ideas like this.
Another pattern that I kept seeing is a
lot of apps show a custom screen before
the notification pop-up. Apparently, it
improves accept rates significantly.
Here's an example by Brilliant. I'll
remind you to learn so it becomes a
long-term habit. Cool.
Center takes it one step further. It
also teases you the notification that
you'll receive if you allow it. This
might explain why web onboarding is 21%
shorter than iOS. Mobile just has more
permission and paywall screens baked in.
Okay, this one surprised me. House split
their sign-up form into multiple screens
and they see a 15% increase in
conversions. Maybe the friction we add
in one place removes friction in
another. Culture plays a role here as
well. Users in Eastern markets tend to
be more comfortable with
information-heavy interfaces. So, what
feels like clutter to one audience feels
efficient to another, which is partly
why we can't just copy what worked. And
I don't think there's one right or wrong
way to design an onboarding flow that's
best in class. The ones that stuck with
me didn't feel like onboarding. What I
saw in common in these apps is that they
brought users to value quickly.
Sometimes it's adding delight to a very
long onboarding flow. Sometimes it's
letting users personalize their app
experience for themselves. And sometimes
it's getting out of the way. So, do we
even need onboarding?
Mobbin is a place to find design
inspiration. The product speaks for
itself. Same with AI chat apps. The
first prompt is where users find value.
For products like these, maybe the best
experience [music] is just to let users
get in fast and not have an onboarding
experience that gets in their way.
Maybe it all boils down to the product.
We had so much fun diving into the data,
and did you know that onboarding flows
are the second most searched on Mobbin?
For the next video, I have a feeling
that we're going to dive really deep
into dashboards and see what the data
tells us. So, stick around. Subscribe if
this vibes with you.